{"tossups": [{"question": "Thousands of soldiers fleeing from this country attempted to surrender to the British after World War II, but they were refused and subsequently massacred in the Bleiburg Repatriation. In this country, one ethnic group barricaded the village of Berak to disrupt a 1990 election, leading to the Log Revolution. It was led during its independence war by Franjo Tudman, also its first president. This country was led during World War II by the fascist Ustase party, and its ports on the Adriatic include Split and Rijeka. For ten points, name this former Yugoslavian republic, a country with capital Zagreb.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Croatia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This character claims that \u201cfive-card stud taught me a lot about mankind.\u201d His wife sings \u201cThis is prophetic!\u201d after receiving a glass elephant, then interrupts a performance of<em> The Red Detachment of</em> <em>Women</em> in Act II. This operatic character claims \u201cthe eyes and ears of history caught every gesture\u201d in\u201cNews Has a Kind Of Mystery,\u201d an aria sung just after he stepped off the<em> Spirit of \u201876</em> and was greeted by Chou En-Lai. For ten points, name this title character of a John Adams opera based on his 1972 visit to China.", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b> (accept<b> Nixon in China</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "Historians have long debated the meaning of this ruler\u2019s last words, \u201cI have made but one mistake.\u201dWhen this ruler complained to his father about a urine tax, his father held up a coin to him and said\u201cmoney does not stink.\u201d This ruler put down the revolt of Terentius Maximus, who pretended to be the former emperor Nero. A monument dedicated to this ruler shows soldiers carrying off treasures like a pair of trumpets and a golden menorah. For ten points, name this Roman emperor whose namesake arch commemorates his destruction of Jerusalem.", "answer": "<b> Titus</b> Vespasianus Augustus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Squatters attempted to establish the Cimmaron Territory in a portion of this state, and a proposed state in its eastern half would have had its capital at Muskogee. This state\u2019s Unassigned Lands were opened up to settlement with the Land Rush of 1889, and the \u201cNeutral Strip,\u201d or \u201cNo Man\u2019s Land,\u201dbecame this state\u2019s western panhandle. The proposed state of Sequoyah would have succeeded the Indian Territory in, for ten points, what Great Plains state just north of Texas?", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One hundred of these objects were initially purchased by William T. Robey, while the other 600 were destroyed. A forgery of one of these objects was found on a Broward County absentee ballot in 2006. These items have recently sold for nearly a million dollars each, despite their printed price of 24 cents, and were made in 1918 to commemorate a new air mail route. For ten points, name these rare United States stamps in which the central object was misprinted upside-down.", "answer": "<b> Inverted Jenny</b> stamps (accept<b> Flying Jenny</b> stamp, accept any description about an <b>upside-down</b> bi<b>plane stamp</b>, but do not require \u201cupside down\u201d or \u201cinverted\u201d after the final word is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This region was ruled in medieval times by the Bilung family, and the city of Meissen in this region was renowned for its porcelain. This region was once split between the Lauenburg and Wittenberg Imperial Circles, and its Wettin rulers split off Thuringia from this region. One city in this region was controversially firebombed by Allied forces during WWII. Dresden is in, for ten points, what German region whose capital is Leipzig?", "answer": "<b> Saxony</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man wrote one story about the impact of war upon Carter Druses\u2019 family in his \u201cA Horseman in the Sky.\u201d This author described the death of Jerome Searing in \u201cOne of the Missing,\u201d and he also wrote a story about a young boy caught up in the battle of Chickamauga. Another story by this author describes the attempted sabotage of Peyton Farquhar before he is hung from title structure. For ten points, name this American author of \u201cAn Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge\u201d who disappeared in 1914 on a trip to see the Mexican Revolution.", "answer": "Ambrose<b> Bierce</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "This document\u2019s Article III states it is the duty of the United states \u201cto furnish each Government named in the Preamble.\u201d John Blaine was the only senator to vote against the ratification of this agreement, which states that the signatories are \u201cDeeply sensible of their solemn duty to promote the\u2014 welfare of mankind.\u201d This document\u2019s stated goal of \u201cuniting the civilized nations of the world in a common renunciation\u201d was not even remotely successful, but its American \u2014 co-sponsor won the 1929 Nobel Peace Prize anyway. For ten points, name this international pact that forbade the use of war for conflict resolution, named for its American and French architects.", "answer": "<b> Kellogg</b>-<b>Briand</b> Pact (accept names in either order; accept<b> Pact of Paris</b>; accept<b> General Treaty for Renunciation of War as an Instrument of National Policy</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country in November 2015, a cargo plane carrying oil workers to the Paloch oil fields crashed after taking off from its capital in Central Equatoria. Riek Machar now leads a People\u2019s Liberation Movement-in-Opposition in a civil war in this country; Machar briefly served as its vice president, but was fired with the rest of this country\u2019s cabinet in July 2013. In that civil war here, Bortown, the capital of Jonglei State, was captured in December 2013. For ten points, name this African country that established its capital at Juba in 2011.", "answer": "Republic of<b> South Sudan</b> (do not accept or prompt Sudan alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One emperor of this region came to power after the signing of the Articles of Favorable Treatment. The Concordia Association was the prevalent party in this region, and it was defeated in the battle of Khalkin Gol. Unit 731, a group of doctors that experimented on humans, operated in this region. Rulers of this region were known as Kangde. It was established after a victorious campaign of the Kwantung army under Hideki Tojo, and it was located in the northern region of China. For ten points, name this puppet state that was located in present day Manchuria.", "answer": "<b> Manchukuo</b> (prompt on Manchuria before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In one story set during this war, characters satirically described as \u201crepresentatives of virtue\u201d ignore the title character, even though she had a picnic basket of food with those characters. In that story, a caravan of refugees from this war accidentally wander into an inn held by the enemy, and are only let go when a prostitute sleeps with the enemy officer. \u201cMademoiselle Fifi,\u201d \u201cBoule de Suif,\u201d [sweef] and many other works of Guy de Maupassant were set during, for ten points, what war that ended the Second French Empire?", "answer": "<b> Franco-Prussian</b> War (or<b> Franco-German</b> War)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This entity was victorious against Grand Duke Vytautas at the battle of the Vorskla river, though it had prior lost to Lithuania at the battle of the Blue Waters. This entity symbolically disintegrated after a stand-off at the Ugra river. Members of this entity filled 9 sacks full of ears following the battle of Legnica, and its greatest triumph took place against the Hungarians at Mohi. For ten points, name this most northwestern of the Mongolian Khanates, founded by Batu Khan in the 1240s, which supposedly received its name from the color of its soldiers\u2019 tents.", "answer": "<b> Golden Horde</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The commission investigating this event found its roots in \u201cun-Americanism\u201d and\u201cpaternalism.\u201d In claiming that this event forced the nation to \u201cthe ragged edge of anarchy,\u201dRichard (+) Olney issued injunctions against several of this event\u2019s leaders, though it took Nelson Miles to finally end it. Grover Cleveland deemed that this event disrupted (*)</b> mail and sent in troops, angering the Governor of Illinois, John Peter Altgeld. Eugene Debs was arrested for his role in, for ten points, what 1894 strike in an Illinois company town by the American Railway Union?", "answer": "<b> Pullman strike</b> (or<b> boycott</b>, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This film ignores the 1845 death of Elizabeth Reed by claiming that Katalin Helenski was the first woman to be executed in her state. Assistant District Attorney Martin Harrison is</b> <b>accused of forging evidence in this film after the death of the (+)</b> <b>Hunyak prompts Fred</b> <b>Casely\u2019s lover to re-hire her lawyer. In this film, a pair of deaths in the Hotel Cicero is detailed along with a set of homicides nicknamed (*)</b> \u201cpop,\u201d \u201csix,\u201d and \u201csquish.\u201d Billy Flynn sings \u201cGive \u2018em the old razzle-dazzle\u201d to win a court case in, for ten points, what 2002 Best Picture Oscar winner, a musical film that stars Catherine Zeta-Jones and Renee Zellweger as murderesses Velma Kelly and Roxie Hart?", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b>After taking power in 2011, this country\u2019s current leader reached cease-fire accords with Shan and Karen insurgents. The supposed expansion of Islam in this country is opposed by the Buddhist monk Ashin Wirathu, and by its (+) 969 Movement. This country is home to a rebel group called the Kachin Independence Army and a Rohingya Muslim minority. It is currently led by (*) </b> Thein Sein, and its opposition National League for Democracy is led by Aung San Suu Kyi [ang san soo chee]. For ten points, name this country that moved its capital to Naypyidaw in 2005.", "answer": "Republic of the Union of<b> Myanmar</b> (or<b> Burma</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>After witnessing one of these events, John Francis decided to go on a journey walking all 48 of the contiguous states by foot. In 1967, Blackburn Buccaneer aircraft sent by the Fleet Air Arm dropped bombs and fuel to limit the damage done by one of these events. A dome nicknamed a (+) \u201csombrero\u201d and the chemical COREXIT failed to completely stop one of these events. One of these disasters was caused by the negligence of Joseph Hazelwood, who drunkenly (*)</b> ran aground in Prince William Sound. For ten points, name these events, the biggest of which began after the<em> Deepwater Horizon</em> blowout in 2010.", "answer": "<b> oil spill</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>These two countries engaged in the battle of Lund, which was instigated by the earlier Treaty of Roskilde. One war between these two countries was known as the Lennart (+) Torstennson war and arose over the collecting of the Sound Dues. Wars between these two countries often contested the region of Scania. The final battle between these two countries was in 1710 at Helsingborg. During the (*)</b> Thirty Years War, the Treaty of Bromesbro was signed between these two countries by Axel Oxenstierna and Christian IV. For ten points, name these two Nordic countries separated by the Oresund strait between the North and Baltic seas.", "answer": "<b> Sweden</b> and<b> Denmark</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This rival of Felix Zuloaga was arrested as part of the Plan of Tacubaya. Shortly after a key victory, the French forced this man to move his capital to San Luis Potosi. Earlier,</b> <b>this man was exiled from (+)</b> <b>Oaxaca [wah-HAH-kah] to New Orleans for his opposition</b> <b>to Santa Anna\u2019s insistance on continuing to fight the Americans. Ignacio Zaragoza served this leader at the Battle of (*) </b> Puebla, after which he was able to restore the republic. Emperor Maximilian was overthrown and replaced by, for ten points, what five-time President of Mexico during the 19th century?", "answer": "Benito<b> Ju\u00b4arez</b> Garcia <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Bacchides avenged this empire\u2019s defeat at Adasa with victory at Elasa. Alexander Balas was a pretender king of this empire. After the battle of Magnesia, this empire was compelled to sign the Treaty of Apamea, which gave their holdings to (+) Pergamum and Rhodes. This empire employed Nicanor, who was defeated by Judas Maccabeus. The founder of this empire received 500 war elephants from (*) </b>Chandragupta Maurya, which were effective in the battle of Ipsus against the Antigonids. Antioch was the capital of this empire. For ten points, name this Hellenistic empire, founded by a former general of Alexander, that included Persia, Mesopotamia, and parts of Anatolia.", "answer": "<b> Seleucid</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}